Singer, songwriter, producer Charlie
Puth has amassed over 35 billion
streams. He also got nine multiplatinum
singles, four Grammy nominations, three
Billboard Music Awards, a Critics's
Choice Award, and a Golden Globe
nomination. Charlie's fourth studio
album, Whatever is Clever, comes out
March 27th of this year. Presented by
Mix with the Masters, this session will
explore how Charlie uses modern
technology to turn ideas into hit songs.
Please welcome Charlie Puth.
[music]
>> We're all here for the love of music.
This is amazing.
There's such an important role as
artists and producers and songwriters in
here.
[music]
>> So I was like, can you give me like
something like a rhythmic? I never like
to start with the drums right away. I
want to have an instrument that kind of
gives percussion in F major. And I I was
like, can you do
and he puts his laptop here and he was
like, here, try this. And [music]
and I'm like [music]
trying to like
I broke my own rule and I was like, "Oh,
maybe I'll put like a little a beat on
it. [music]
And I was like still coming up with
[__] nothing. And it wasn't until I
opened up Keyscape and put on Hold on,
let me put this on solo latch really
quickly. So we have the guitar part. Do
you know the plugin by Tal Tal the
chorus? The Juno chorus. I took I wanted
a Phil Collins vibe. I had this [music]
and then it all opened up when I did.
[music]
Listen how beautiful this is when it
comes in. It's just bass and piano.
[clears throat]
[music]
Little loops on top of it.
Okay, now I need a garbage pan snare.
Kind of shitty on its own. And then
Larry,
[music]
I'm a firm believer that not everything
has to sound good on its own. If it
sounds good in the mix, that's kind of
good enough.
That sounds like I just made my first
beat ever, right? [music]
But listen to what happens when you put
everything together.
[music]
Little double kick kind of
add the big.
[music]
Let's loop that part.
Tom's overhead
and then the main loop which is like the
the juice to everything. [music]
See that's the woo that I was expecting
for when I put that in. That's it right
there.
[music and singing]
>> That melody is not getting in the way.
Like you It's like I want a stem to be a
chorus. I think that's what we should
all strive when we're producing a record
to have something the the common
listener might not even catch, but like
they might catch it.
>> [music]
>> So, I'm sorry to blue balls you here,
but
>> I was like, we need a choir.
Listen to [singing]
different day and night
>> very low.
[music]
>> And of course that's just counteracting
my [music]
>> Where's my lead vocal? Where is it? make
me look good. Here it is. [music]
>> So, we have
[music]
>> there's [music] been and then another
round of it.
Beautiful. I can feel the distance.
Everything's different. [music]
Backstory. I had a friend when I went to
Berkeley. He unfortunately passed away
two years prior to me writing this song,
but he always told me when he was alive
that I would write a song like this. And
I never knew what he meant. He was like,
"One day the music industry is going to
it's going to evolve and you're going to
be in it." I'm like, "Sure, whatever you
say." His name was Veil. He always told
me that I would write this song, but he
never sung it. There was no melody or
anything like that. He always just said
I was going to write it. Two years
later, I walk into this room with my
friend Justin. And uh his he goes by DJ
Frankie. It's he's who I made the song
with. I heard these chords. It was like
a very again it was 2014. It was a very
like synthet I'm I'm not going to bother
finding a synth here. It was very down
[music]
and had the sweeps and all, you know,
white noise filters,
all that stuff. And I was like, you know
what? We're we're we're adding and
building to this track and it's nothing.
This is just an example of one of my
processes. It's why don't we just delete
everything? and we just added sounds for
two hours and we still have no song
instead of it being
what if it's
and the moment I did that I kid you not
I got chills right now the moment I did
that it it's been a long day [music]
without you [singing] and I'll tell you
all about it when I see you again I was
singing to my friend And I realized this
was the song that he was talking about.
This was the song that [music] he told
me that I would write one day. Music is
such an amazing thing, everybody. We're
so fortunate to be here. I hate to be a
broken record, but we have such an
important
we have such an important role as we
have such an important role as artists
and producers [music] and songwriters in
here in the day and age where everything
is, you know, people are having birthday
parties and they're just typing in, you
know, birthday party music and it's all
artificially made. This is the most
important time to be human right now.
In a broad way of saying my process
varies. One day I'll, you know, make the
whole track and write the whole song.
[music] One day it'll take a month. It
just patience is key. And I think that's
a good way to end it all.
I want to thank you all for coming out
today and taking the time to
listen to this and stay creative. Thank
you very much everybody. Thank you.
[music]
Superman got none
of